Hi there, students, again.
So there was some issue with the internet.
So therefore, I have to cut the previous video
and start from this second video.
So I want you to talk about the second point, OK?
So another example of a self-serving bias is that most people take personal credit
for their success and blame outside forces for their failures.
For example, some students
may kind of
attribute their good grades, such as their A's and B's, to themselves, such as their intelligence,
right? Their quick grasp of the material, or maybe good study skills, right?
So on the contrary, they may sometimes attribute their poor grades
to something outside of their control, right?
Something
such as having an unfair teacher, having a
maybe some type of maybe
disease, maybe flu on the day of exam, for example, right?
And so on. And the third one, like the third self-serving bias is our inclination
to exaggerate
or place a greater value on our strengths and underestimate or downplay our weaknesses.
So we tend to rank traits or abilities that we have such as sense of humor maybe,
intelligence, higher importance, and to the very abilities we like
or we are weak in.
For example, we can see such tendency maybe in the doctors also.
The book gives us statistics
of the
wrong diagnosis or
overconfidence of doctors, right, which led to eventual deaths of patients,
right? So sometimes doctors may be too overconfident, right, and they may kind of try
not to dig
deep into the
diagnosis, right, of the patients, and they may give a wrong diagnosis to people, right, and
which may eventually lead to some
misfortunes for the patients.
And the next kind of error
in our thinking is self-fulfilling prophecy.
Maybe you have heard about this term, right?
And self-fulfilling prophecy occurs when our exaggerated or distorted expectations
reinforce actions
that actually bring about the expected event.
So our beliefs about the world tell us what we might expect from other people and situations.
And this cognitive shortcut provides a kind of energy saving way of understanding the world
around us.
And when our expectations are kind of true,
accurate, we can make decisions more efficiently than if we had to examine all the evidence.
And however, this cognitive shortcut can also lead to errors by oversimplifying the way things
really are.
So here we can give some examples such as from the Great Depression from the USA, which happened
in 1930s, right? When
in panic, a few people started to kind of take back their money from the
banks, which eventually kind of spread to many other people and which
eventually led to this kind of crisis, right?
And the second example can be that maybe in the class, we may
have a certain
sportsman, right? Certain professional football player, for example, right?
And
when the teacher, for example, when if me, I have this self-fulfilling prophecy, so I may have
bias towards the student thinking that since he's a professional footballer, so he may expect
most of his time playing football and not studying, right?
So he may be just coming to classes to get this
attendance, right? And based on this, maybe I may not pay much attention or the other teachers
may not pay attention to this student, right?
May not kind of entertain him, may not give chance to him to talk, right?
And eventually this guy, or maybe this girl, right?
They may lose the kind of interest in this class, in this subject, And eventually, in the end
of the semester, they may get some mediocre grade, right?
So, which will lead to kind of a term such as self-fulfilling prophecy that
since the beginning,
the teacher or the professor thought that this guy is kind of not a good
student. And eventually, the actions of the professor himself or herself led to
that result, okay?
And the last
theme in our today's lecture is about the social errors and biases.
And we know that people, or we humans, we are kind of social creatures, right?
And because of this feature, so social norms and cultural expectations exert a strong influence
on how we perceive the world.
So much so that we tend to perceive the world differently in groups,
from the way we do in isolation.
So we know that, right? Maybe from even our own experiences,
we may behave maybe differently when we are alone, right?
In some occasions. However, if together we are with our friends, right?
With other guys or girls together, right?
We may completely react differently to the similar event, right?
And the groups can systematically distort both the guessing and interpretation of evidence.
And there are several
social errors and biases, as you guys can see
in your screen. So first of them is one of us or one of them issue or error.
So our brains seem to be programmed to classify people as either
ours or one of us, or they, or one of them, okay?
So like my tribe and their tribe, or kind of the people from my country
or my family and the other, for example, right?
And we tend to treat people who are similar to us with respect and those who are different
from us, whether in regard to race,
gender, religion, political party, age, or nationality, with suspicion and wars.
And here comes a question to you guys.
Can you guys think about some historical or maybe
current day
global events or just cases
where
such biases occurred and led to some disasters in the places, in countries?
Thank you, guys. I hope you all had some great ideas.
And of course, I think you mentioned one of the kind of points in regards to this
error is maybe racism, right?
Like kind of classifying people, right?
Based on the race, right?
Based on the color, maybe, right?
That maybe
in the Middle Ages, right?
In the middle centuries,
the Europeans, right? Mainly from the global north, right?
These people, when they were invading the people on the south, right?
Or the, how we call the developing countries now.
So these parts, maybe
they had the similar kind of views, right?
Similar
worldview was their kind of driver, right?
They were kind of thinking that they are different or maybe based on that race or based on
their kind of religion or whatever else, that they're kind of privileged or they have a certain
kind of
characteristics. However, they or others or those living in these Asian countries
or African countries or these in
South American countries, they're different, right?
So they don't possess certain kind of features, certain traits, and therefore, we
need to kind of
help them, right? We need to save them, or we need to kind of
educate them, or like the people, like even now,
some kind of follow this idea that we need to save the woman, right?
They also have this, such type of biases, okay?
And this error also contributes to our tendency to polarize issues into two
camps, okay? So whether it be maybe right wing or left wing, right?
Whether it be maybe
capitalist, socialist, right?
And so on.
And
according to the scientists, If we are to overcome this social error, we need to be consciously
aware of it in our thinking and to build in protective measures.
As critical thinkers, we can walk towards minimizing this error in our thinking
by first critically evaluating the situation and then consciously reprogramming our brains
to come up with new, more reasonable definitions of who it is that we view as us by seeking
a more immediate and inclusive basis for a connection such as we all live in the same dorm,
we all attend the same college, right?
We are all maybe the citizens of Uzbekistan or
we are all human beings, right?
We do not maybe only need to divide people like based on their
nationalities, for example, right?
We are all human beings at the end of the day.
And
we also need to make a conscious effort
to be open to multiple perspectives, even those we are initially convinced must be mistaken.
And the next error is social expectations.
So social expectations can be so powerful that they may lead to collective delusions in which
people attempt to fit evidence into their cultural worldview.
Sometimes these social errors may even become institutionalized acting on social expectations
without subjecting them to critical analysis can have dire consequences.
And as we have seen in the case in the beginning with Peter Raleigh, right, that this policeman,
they had these biases, right, this kind of social expectations, right,
and
they had this sort of thinking, kind of expectations about
the mother being, having certain kind of type of character, and therefore, this guy
should have acted based on this kind of behavior, right?
So therefore, kind of police came, I mean, maybe based on this conclusion, based on this expectation,
they made this claim, right?
And stereotyping is another type of social bias based on social expectations about individuals
that are based on socially generated group levels, labels.
And another error or bias is called
group pressure and conformity.
And group pressure can influence individual members to take positions that they would never
support by themselves, okay?
As we have seen
in the case of the prison experiment in the previous lectures.
Some religious cults
may exploit this tendency by separating their members from the dissenting views
of families and friends.
Group pressure is so powerful in shaping how we see the world that it can even lead people
to deny contrary evidence that is right before their eyes.
And the desire for agreement is normal.
However, this desire when combined with our innate tendency to divide the world into one of
us and one of them can lead to the exclusion of those who disagree with the majority, okay?
And in addition, people tend to prefer being around people
who agree with them, right?
We usually may not like being together with those who kind of
object to our views and opinions.
And
one of the
terms
or errors in this regards is called groupthink, right?
So sometimes
we may be having some type of group meeting, right?
Or maybe discussion, right?
And let's imagine that
someone from this group, maybe with a higher authority, or maybe
with higher GPA, or maybe with other kind of difference, right, to whom
Most of the people kind of believe or respect, right?
He or she comes up with some ideal
kind of way or brilliant idea, right?
And then all of us kind of tend to follow that idea, right?
And then eventually come to the kind of
similar conclusion, right?
And then we kind of...
commit this type of mistake, which is called groupthink, right?
Rather than kind of following the evidence and critical thinking, right?
We're just following the group, okay?
And another example, maybe from your own real life can be that Since you guys are about to
graduate this year and many of you or some of you may be considering or may start considering
about getting married, right?
Or maybe you start already getting this pressure, right?
So imagine, so now maybe you may not have much pressure, but later on when you go to work
and if you're still not married, right?
You may start having more pressure, right?
From your peers, from your relatives, right?
And from others. Or even another example, right?
Maybe because of this group pressure, maybe if
it's only left to your own decision, maybe you would want
to conduct or to make your wedding, you know, maybe more calm and more kind
of
different
atmosphere, right? Maybe you may not even do the wedding itself, right?
Maybe you just want to have kind of a small event.
together with your close relatives and maybe spend that money to something else.
So, however, because all this group pressure, right?
Because you guys or you girls are attending the events or the weddings of your peers, of your
friends, right? Everybody's attending everybody's
social events. Then maybe eventually when you are doing
or when it's time for your own wedding, for your own ceremony, you may have this kind of subconscious,
right? Unconsciousness.
group pressure, right? That you have to do also, you have to kind of go through these similar
rituals, right? You may also have to kind of maybe
use similar services or maybe invite similar amount of guests, right?
Or maybe do certain type of activities, right?
So however, as we have seen, so
maybe we need to use or access more of our critical thinking skills, right?
And the last kind of theme or error in this regards is diffusion of
responsibility. So
this is a kind of a social phenomenon that occurs in groups of people about a critical size.
So if responsibility is not explicitly assigned to us, we tend to regard it as not our problem
or as belonging to someone else.
For example, we are much more likely to come to someone's aid If we are alone, then if we are
in a crowd. So I think this is a normal, right?
This may have happened in our daily lives, right?
Maybe in the places
where we see that there is no one else
to help or to kind of assist in that situation.
Of course, we feel kind of obligation.
Whereas when there are many people, we may try to kind of,
group right, right? Maybe group right in this situation, right?
Or maybe we may just kind of think that the other people
may do the work instead, right?
And here the book gives us a very,
not a good, but a
tragic life example.
And it's called Bystander Apathy or the Kitty-Genevers Syndrome.
So in
1964, 28-year-old Kitty Genovese was murdered outside
her New York City apartment building.
And her killer left twice
when people in the building turned on their lights.
Before he came back a third time and killed her.
In the half hour that lapsed during the attack,
none of the
Genovese
38 neighbors who had heard her repeated cries for help called the police.
So this is a very
tragic example
for this bias, which is called diffusion of responsibility.
This was all for this lecture.
However, before we finish our today's lecture, let me play you
one video and give you a task based on this, okay?
So,
specifically, intentionally, I have chosen the
shorter version.
And if you are interested, you can find out longer versions of this video, okay?
So I hope that my screen is visible to you guys.
So let me.
At a time when few people were aware of the damage being done to our environment, marine biologist
and writer Rachel Carson demanded that the US government take responsibility to protect people
and the planet.
Born in 1907 in Springdale, Pennsylvania, Carson was fascinated by the animal and plant life
that surrounded her 65-acre family farm.
As she grew, her love for nature grew too.
At Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore, she studied zoology and genetics.
After graduating, she took a job with the federal government's U.S.
Bureau of Fisheries, where she studied the effects of DDT, an insect killer the government
promoted to farmers. Carson noticed it killed wildlife and called for a reduction in its use.
When the government did nothing, she wrote a book.
Published in 1962, Silent Spring caused a sensation.
Using language ordinary people could relate to, Carson exposed how harmful the pesticide could
be to animals, plants, and humans.
It sold 65,000 copies in just two weeks.
The book caused so much controversy that Carson became the target of a smear campaign, financed
in part by the chemical industry itself.
But she was determined to educate the American public about the realities of DDT.
She went on TV, spoke at conferences, and even testified to Congress, calling on the government
to take action.
Sadly, Carson passed away just two years after Silent Spring was published.
But many agree that her work contributed toward the creation of the Environmental Protection
Agency in 1970, which phased out the use of DDT.
By raising public awareness, Rachel Carson was a major force in pressuring the government and
the people to take responsibility for the environment.
What issues do you think we can take more responsibility for?
Okay, this is not your question.
I will give you another question.
So let me stop sharing the screen.
Okay, guys, I hope you watched this video about the biologist and author
Rachel Carson. OK, so as we have seen, she was an incredible lady and scientist.
Right.
And based on this, I want to give you a question and you need to have you need to
write your ideas about it.
And intentionally, I will not write down the equation in the Moodle in E-Class because even
though I specifically mentioned to use your own brain and your own experiences
and not use AI, some of you guys, some of you smart guys
or maybe hardworking guys
use the AI, right? So
why to do it? Okay, guys. So therefore, I think it would be easier for you guys, rather than
typing all this to AI, just to think maybe for five minutes and spend another five minutes
to write down your answers.
So here comes the question.
Think of a time
when you used a rational argument to defend a position that was supported by credible
evidence, even though
doing so angered or alienated a family member or teacher, or employer,
or someone else, or your friends maybe.
So what was the outcome? Was it worth it?
And if so, why?
So
I hope that the question is clear, is not just difficult.
It also comes with this similar logic as our first quiz.
So please use your own judgment, your own experience, and try to answer this question
by just simple words, okay?
Nothing is complicated and there are no right or wrong answers.
Okay guys, thank you very much and see you next time.